## Nikolai Zhdanov

## Java Software Engineer

#### **Profile**

As a Software Engineer with over 7 years of experience, I specialize in developing distributed and scaled systems. Over the past 5 years, I have focused on developing microservice applications using Java/Kotlin. I also utilize the DevOps methodology to create reliable and high-performance infrastructure.

#### Contact

Tbilisi, Georgia

+995 550 059 499

nikolai@zhdanov.dev

LinkedIn: @nikolai-zhdanov

## **Education background**

## Vyatka State University of Humanities

Computer Science, Mathematics and Physics Faculty

Bachelor of Applied
Mathematics
and Computer Science

#### **Skills & Proficiencies**

Java/Kotlin ■■■■■

Spring

Framework  $\blacksquare \blacksquare \blacksquare \blacksquare \blacksquare$ 

Redis ■■■■

Kubernetes

Mongo DB

Ansible

React ■■■

TypeScript ■■■

# **Courses &** certifications

Java Software Engineer Course

## **Innopolis University**

January 2017 Gained a diploma in Java Backend Engineering

## **Work Experience**

#### **Senior Software Engineer (Bootcamp)**

Yandex, the biggest IT company in Russia

May 2023 - August 2023

Stack: Java, Grpc, Spring, YDB.

#### **Functions:**

- Acquaintance with the projects of 4th teams
- Development of gRPC API

#### Results:

- Implemented the storage of alarm details in the monitoring system, which can handle petabytes of data.
- Fixed an issue in the deployment process of Yandex Cloud.

#### **Senior Software Engineer**

Alfa-bank, the largest private bank in Russia

June 2020 - May 2023

Stack: Java/Kotlin, Spring Framework, Redis, Hazelcast, MongoDB, Ansible,

Mesos, Kubernetes

#### **Functions:**

- Creating API and business logic for mobile applications at Alfa-Bank.
- Enhancing the reliability and performance of services.
- Writing ansible playbooks to configure and deploy infrastructure.
- Providing guidance and support to new employees and interns.

## Results:

- Successfully implemented multiple APIs with a production capacity of over 500 requests per second.
- Created a monitoring application for Zeebe, similar to Camunda Operate, using the React framework.
- Provided training and mentorship to an intern, helping them develop their skills as a Java Software Engineer.

## Senior Software Engineer

Lorus SCM, an expert in the field of logistics

February 2019 - June 2020

**Stack**: Java, Kotlin, Spring Framework, PostgreSQL, MongoDB, RabbitMQ, Apache poi, Apache Kafka, Docker swarm, Redis, Elastic search, Camunda BPM

## Functions:

- Design microservice architecture.
- Leading a team of developers as a team lead.
- Configuring infrastructure: Docker swarm, Mongo DB, Redis, etc.

## Results:

- Implemented the CI/CD system using Gitlab CI and Docker swarm, resulting in improved safety and reduced time to production to 10 minutes.
- Developed core services including authentication service and communication service.
- Integrated Camunda into the system.
- Effectively led a team of 5 developers.

## Mentor for students in Java Software Engineering

Innopolis University, The first university to specialize in Computer Science in Russia

January 2019 - February 2022

## Functions:

- Reviewing homework
- Consulting students, and providing support

#### Results:

• 31 out of 35 students gained a diploma in Java Backend Engineering.

#### **Software Engineer**

Magnit, one of Russia's biggest food retail chains

May 2018 - February 2019

Stack: Java, Spring Framework, AMQP, PostgreSQL, MSSQL, RabbitMQ, Apache poi, JDBC.

#### **Functions:**

- Refactoring existing systems to use microservice architecture.
- Supporting legacy system.
- Mentoring junior java developers.
- Deployment apps from bare metal, configuring Nginx.

#### Results:

- Optimized legacy code to give output in real time. This system previously had a lag of 2 hours.
- Successful implementation of a data bus.
- Optimised the transport distribution routes for orders, increasing the efficiency of deliveries

#### **Software Engineer**

Sberbank, the largest bank in Russia

January 2017 - May 2018

Stack: Java, Jave EE, PL/Sql.

#### **Functions:**

- Developing adapters between database and data bus.
- Developing data pipeline (models) in Oracle database.
- Deploying apps to WebSphere.

#### Results:

- Implementation of product to production for over 100 billions users: replenishment of cards and accounts through external participants.
- Implemented xslt transformation library.

## PHP Software Engineer

I-Butler project, a plugin to find the best offers for customers

February 2016 - December 2016

Stack: PHP5, MySQL, YII2, Beanstalkd.

## **Functions:**

- Designing architecture and db models.
- Writing technical documentation.
- Development of the API.

## Results:

- Refactored legacy code to process big data.
- Implemented calculation of points for big users graph.

## Electronic circuit design engineer

Project Smartcoin, startup developed smart card for payment and loyalty system

December 2014 - December 2015

Stack: C++, microcontrollers series Atmel ATMega, Texas InstrumentsCC25xx,

IAR Embedded Workbench, Altium design.

## Functions:

- Designing a circuit of devices.
- Developing a software on devices.

## Results:

• Created a prototype device and software for it.